welcome to another interesting video in our previous video we discussed decision
making on the certainty decision making on the uncertainty position making on the risk
we have been able to explain all these concepts using typical example in this video we want to
talk about decision tree how do we analyze this decision situation using decision tree at the
end of this lesson learners should be able to use decision tree to analyze the decision situation
I'm Abdullah Oqayami Faladeh I'm the operation research facilitator which would explain the
details of how to analyze the decision situation using decision tree what do you need by decision tree
a decision tree is one of the tools being used for diagrammatic presentation of a sequential a
multi-dimensional aspect of a particular decision problem for systemic analysis and evaluation so it is
a tool the message that is decision tree is a tool that involves the use of diagrams to show the
sequential and multi-dimensional aspect of particular decision problem
when using decision tree your decision problem the alternative cost of action the state of nature and the
likely outcomes the likely outcomes that's the probability estimate of alternatives
the likely outcomes of alternatives are diagrammatic or graphically depicted as branches
as sub-branches of a horizontal tree
now
I'm happy to tell you that decision tree is highly useful to a decision maker in multi-stage situation
which involves a series of decisions each dependent on the preceding one so when you have a multi-stage
situations which involves an iterative decision process such that each dependent on the preceding one
decision tree is best used in that situation
more so decision tree analysis allow you to understand simply by inspection you can view it
is a visualization approach which shows various assumptions and alternative in a graphic form
and it is more easier to understand than the abstract analytical form we have been used to
now let's move into a typical typical example of how to solve
problem how to analyze decision situation using decision tree
so we have this payoff table which represents the possible profit associated with erection of a building on the land
i want to try to draw a decision tree for the problem
and also the timing the up the best optimal course of action
so this is very simple compared to the analytical approach here we go you can see
we have three states of nature shopping complex d1 high-rise houses d2 blocks of plants d3
so this will be the first three branches that will come out of a node and you can see that here
so we have three branches d1 d2 and d3 for each of these decision alternatives
we have how many states of nature we have three states of nature low medium and high so that means from each
decision alternative three branches comes out of it and that is why you can see here
that in decision alternative d1 we have three branches coming out of it
same thing for d2 three branches coming out of it
same thing for deep three branches coming out of it
and also you can see that there's probability estimates for each state of nature we have 0.25 0.3 0.45
and that's what we apply here 0.25 0.3 0.45 0.25 0.3 0.45 0.25 0.3 0.45 and at the same time we look for the
corresponding payoff value so for d1
the first branch the first branch takes 200 pay of value which is under the 0.25 probability estimate
100 for medium which is another 0.3 probability estimate 400 for high which is under 0.45 probability
estimate and that's what we have here under d1 so we apply the same thing under d2 and we apply the same thing
under d3 and from here from this decision diagram
decision tree you can see that it will be easier for us to determine the expected monetary value
for d1 which is going to be 0.25 times 200 plus 0.3 times 100 plus 0.45 times 400
the same thing goes to d2 the expected monetary value for d2 is 0.25 times 100 plus 0.3 times 150
plus 0.45 times 300 when you also go to expected monetary value for d3 now 0.25 times 300 plus 0.3 times
200 plus 0.45 times 400 and that makes it very easier to compute unlike when you are computing directly
from the table and from that we have the computation here so the expected monetary value for d1 gives 260
for d2 gives 205 and for d3 gives 285 so in conclusion for best optimal cost of action we recommend
that decision maker should adopt decision alternative d3 since it is a decision alternative with the highest
expected value i hope you've learned one or two things in this video to enjoy more videos and to learn more
through this channel press like subscribe if you are yet to do so and press the notification bell
we have some practice questions for you to practice and evaluate yourself
to challenge yourself when you understand in the best decision tree from this short video thanks for
listening bye for now